I just wanted to show you this. This is.
I mentioned it before,
and if you haven't, I've been in the room when I was talking about it.
This is the granola skill.
So if you go to Tessl.io registry,
native dev AI, native Dev
Con 2026, LDN.
I know it just trips off the tongue. There was.
I was told there was to be a QR code, but I wanted to show you this
because it excited me
when I saw it, and I think that it probably will excite you within here.
This is the skill of all the talks that are being recorded on granola.
And you can go in here, you can find your talks that you've been to.
You can go and question them.
You can go and look at them.
So please do take a look at this.
I haven't had a chance to explore it yet because I'm hosting the stage.
So I only saw the URL and thought I'll open that up,
but I wanted to tell you about it. Please take a look.
Please do feedback to the Tessl team how you find using it
and yeah, enjoy exploring it.
In the meanwhile, I am going to shut down my laptop again
and let's get Simon and Rob's slides
set back up.
Last.
To remind everybody if you haven't already,
there were some additional slots for the workshops this afternoon,
so do take a look at the app if you have to hard refresh your app.
There were.
We've increased the number of spaces in this room so that there is a little bit
more capacity than there was before, so there may be some workshop spaces left.
If you're lucky enough to have a workshop
space, please do arrive on time for the workshop.
They will be letting people in and then after a certain period of time,
they will allow the people who are on the waitlist through.
So just make sure you're on time
for those workshops so I can see that Simon and Rob are ready.
So Simon and Rob, can I please welcome you to the stage?
Can you please give it up for Simon Obstbaum and Rob Willoughby?
They're going to be talking about from Vibes to Metrics
and how to actually measure what your agents actually do.
So what we're here to talk to you today is really kind of assess
what you're doing and real work situations.
So a lot will be done before we have to be very cool that they're going quick.
Does this seem like it's producing the right thing to do
and just a software engineering?
That's an interesting one.
We also think that that's not true.
Is it just one wall.
And then you're going to lean more towards that, actually understanding what's
going on behind and actually understanding how you can help improve that.
So I think everyone wanted to go on up.
We've got two different views on how do you get the metrics
top down, looking at correlational studies across a whole bunch of
up, really zooming in on
how many uses one skill to complete one skip.
So in terms of we are all I will get and I'm going to continue with Simon
some as a researcher with the Software Engineering Productivity Research Group
at Stanford, missing both sides of this from CTO and industry,
and then also from the researching and consulting view.
The research focuses on the macro view of adoption across the industry
from that dimension before.
So really looking at how
I say here and specifically 1 in 1
model are able to perform on a single task using a set of context,
a set of scripture that I'm going to test about this morning to support.
Okay.
So here we want now first of all we are going to
soon one step out.
So at the Stanford SEPR Lab
we put together the largest software engineering productivity study.
And we currently have roughly 150,000 engineers
that are in one way or another enrolled in the study.
The companies that we that we work with
committed to a one year period.
In that period, we look at their entire source
code repository, all of their engineers across all other programing languages,
and we try to observe behavior patterns, changes in the data
that has been shared in, in a number of media outlets.
The first piece that we covered was Repair By published
a piece on AI engineers, found that roughly 10% of the engineers.
And if you think meaningful
between the organization one form or another.
And but we do get featured in
the bigger media
as well and on research to relevant conferences.
So when we have a pretty
big data set, many organizations involved,
the first problem is how we understand what's going on.
So what we wanted to find is a better way to deliver it than just counting,
committed counting, counting cars, looking at lines of code.
And so we spent a lot of time into thinking,
how could we help with and and subsequently productivity.
So what we found to work is
that we had here
he writes the code, and then we have a kind of experts
who look at the code and we ask them a set of questions,
and we ask them to questions along the lines of, okay,
how long do you think it took the first to implement this?
How long?
How long do you think it would be taking you to implement this?
And other questions to maintain ability and flexibility?
Then we found out that in that panel and also cross
handles, people tend to be very high agreement.
And to me I've been in engineering meetings
that that was a big surprise, that that was the first prize of the study,
that people can actually agree on something now.
Right.
And and since
we have this high agreement and coordinating also quite nicely
without backtrack, we can have certain tickets, we have the time spent some time.
So from any way you looked at it kind of okay.
So we now how do we run it a tail.
So we did the model.
We put it in addition learning model.
And with that we were able to run at scale.
So basically what we tend to and what strategies is we
look at the analysis through the machine learning model of that tries
to replicate the expert panel.
All right.
Now with with that context being said, I'll be presenting a few ideas
and then take you back to the lower level to understand how
working we
I will show you a little bit on on how
I is impacting teams.
So this is the time.
So we looked at 46 teams that
we've been looking at them over 501 period.
At one point in the study,
we kind of have to change the methodology a little bit.
So for us it was important that we
that we find that the keys.
So we look at the difference.
We're kind of 4.25 in terms of Asian.
And we then
against these that that didn't see the problem
that encountered at one point here was that basically everyone's
trying to build a kind of the control kind of
control went away, however.
So we have to adapt the methodology into line.
But overall what what you can see.
So there wasn't a big difference between teams that that would be using AI
and teams that are using the I or even the teams that using I.
And now you can see over time that basically has has.
So over like 5% different difference in 2023.
In 2003 you can see it like up to 60%
difference in July 2026.
Just to give you some kind of exciting things are going,
yeah.
Now if we look at this on a on a team level,
you can see also that the discrepancy
per team is is vastly different.
So the laggards there's no meaningful
change and output the bottom
25th fifth percentile is doing better.
But when you look top to bottom it's a it's a very it's
a very meaningful difference in terms of in terms of health. And.
Now in in terms of.
Looking out inside of the teams
and looking at the individuals, we see that, you know,
and I think everyone here in this room encountered someone.
You have an individual's that, you know, maybe they may not like it.
Are we into it.
Study in just kind and adopted kind of need it.
And there is an.
It's a significant difference.
It's the biggest difference that we've ever seen to be honest
I started this study in in 2020.
That's going to be, you know, thought about how do we measure productivity.
For me, I had worked in Silicon Valley and the connector
was something that I really liked and a certain extent,
and I wanted to show that it doesn't exist and it didn't exist.
But over time, we're starting to see it now.
So people that know how to create agents, people that know how to work, they
they achieve significantly better outcomes.
Now. On top of that,
and I think this is a really interesting side in terms of
how performance shifting.
So once here is the top and the bottom again.
And we
saw a pretty high rank ability direct.
The pivoted was 0.70.
Yeah.
And policy it dropped to 0.45.
So we believe also like that the tactics that anybody looking to get to perform
no longer enabling you to get top performer today.
So what we believe is what happens
to be honest, a lot of other people from the
the top performers, they move to the to the top performance.
One hypothesis is that like these were people
that were coding would be using the teams.
And now in terms of how maybe some of that automated, some
that have got 15 way and now they became the top of form.
So arguably that's the hypothesis is right.
I don't understand why because observed that happens.
They were busy helping others deliver something delivered good outcomes.
But now they have time and they're killing it.
Yeah.
But we also see that, you know, previously
people performing the top are going down.
Other than that from from from the to
you see most of the, you know a downward.
So that's what we observe in terms of
changing landscape.
Yeah.
Now moving on
to something somewhat more technical.
What we're doing is starting to look at how people
orchestrate their agents.
And we look at that loft patterns.
We see in terms of what we see in the positive
and what the artifacts could possibly be.
So this is a brief from the paper.
We submitted it to ace.
It's it's part of the IEEE Automation Software Engineering Conference.
And it'll happen in the quarter.
So we don't have to pay for how the peer reviews
and the peer reviews are available.
And
so we look at the artifacts, we we look at the embeddings
and assign medals and correlate levels with the output of measurement
that we have shown in the beginning.
So just when you look at control system for levels.
So in terms of scientific foundations.
This comes back to the strong.
And we we can see the impact of this is quite clear.
So in terms of looking at it and it it is like beautiful.
Now what does it mean.
When you look
at it we see repos adopted by config.
So once we start recording and run on it and you don't have any harnessing
tooling instruction skills or whatnot, we see that in terms of,
you know, change after agent.
It's just that, you know, you see more difficult
to be more Saturday mornings codification.
The volume is changing.
But it's just
yeah, it just it feels like
so the tooling and instrumentation is essential to it.
Now when we look at L2
you see a significant increase in your foot.
You see.
Even a decrease
in verb qualification goes down,
goes down.
So all metrics that we analyzed
are actually now improving today with applying.
And that wasn't always in the beginning.
A lot of the argument in the feeds that didn't want an adopted as a
little just introduce defects
within wrote.
And we don't see that anymore in level
two, level three teams.
Now, I think with that I'm happy to get over to
to Rob, who will tell you a little bit how to optimize
into the details of WP.
Cool.
So I hope that to convince you that that structure and actually kind
of the things that we care about in terms of the quality of the goodness,
what I want to do now is to go into a little bit of a deep dive
in terms of how do we put that structure in place,
using skills kind of as the artifact to focus on there.
This is the switch from that to the bottom.
So we've got our review finding to with presenting.
And I think the observation over 150,000 engineers and creating
kind of three times, once you've got that structure in context
of information sharing at the same speed or faster.
So next to kind of
just a single task and a single purpose that we're going to use
to influence the age of that house,
which in this case, the skill and the skill is that still free?
Or you're just talking about the things that I want you to keep in mind is cool.
The work is getting, finishing the way we're seeing,
still getting shifts at the same level of the the hospital still getting.
So if you've got this idea of structure, what's that supposed to be changing?
What is that structure having?
So as I say, just because
but what changes is the agentic for us?
It's the construction of the theorem.
I want to talk a little bit about what kind of task
and what I mean by full completion and introduction.
Following so that we're running is we've got 500 skills.
We have 1000 tasks.
We got 1920s, 19 are complement of models and purposes.
So we got 19 permutations of different models, different rises
because those have had on each other and also affect the performance.
And then the trust that we're using those that are or a synthetic.
But the their branding skill itself, they're meant to be something
that they could expect skill to trigger for.
So if you don't feel I want to say, how do you in place
API security, the task that we're going to construct that that is
great.
Or change the authentication from password to some other mechanism for that,
or something else that might not be related
to expect them to be picking up on the security and looking for that.
And so hopefully potentially not trying to do
like super hard pushing boundaries here.
Think of it as kind of like well scoped to your tickets and expecting engineers
to be getting that one.
And so we see that
hitting a threshold of 1,993% of us,
whether it's in their office in holding, this is the metrics
that are specifically in the agenda, what they do.
So if you have your own internal design for how you want to do whatever you hold
or to make sure that you're updating two supervision versus another,
that's the information that we did in the skill
and then encoded in the instruction following improvement that we see there.
One really interesting thing about that number specifically
is that we see 55% following the instructions of skill.
Even when the skill is not present,
that means the information that is encoded in the skill.
That's actually the weights of the model ready.
And so when you're talking to you, it was getting rid of anyway.
So that means that's actually valuable because burning inference
tokens and paying money down in Google
when the model is going to get in ways that they can get to do that.
So you're giving this will be finishing.
But the things that you care about,
the structure of these skills or changes, how it does it and how well it does it.
So so that's
what what it said,
something changed that the position stays the same.
But is it done?
It's not improved meant jump.
And here I dug into three categories
on what specifically that we see repeated one
gradient guy forces you might not have sell sell guidelines.
You might say, hey, we're going to allow us
to use this set of libraries when we want to do that, to use,
or we have to make sure that we're not going in and we think
that it is what is it, 70 days.
But then again, so those that information is going to be
agencies are going to know.
And so what are you going to do.
Whatever is in there are parts that, hey, if you want to hit this users that out
the service, you also need to configure the API credentials in your argument.
This way you need to make sure you have the land that is going to to apply,
so that gets deployed before he goes, and the rest are going to have that time.
That's information that you need to set up
that they are going to know.
And then finally prohibited or deprecated patterns.
Maybe you really don't ever want an agent to create something
that is exposed to the internet and it goes through or.
You can just give it another unless you have to.
So again, what is that you need that you need of how you
want agency automating.
So this is kind of a concrete example that we found that I found interesting.
So there's a lot of focus as you might
have had an old CI
rates and a client feature.
And whenever the computer taking case
came in after model training data costs for all of the recent frontier models.
So you might say, hey agent, go implement this when you take
my script using that isn't working.
It's going to read it on the left.
And when the programs that community like anchors on, they don't want you
to be passing your potential as not as part of long enough token.
And so it's you can do the old thing and we see this because the old thing,
if you're just looking at cost confusion because it's not a building,
doesn't agree that this thing because it's like
if there's a lot of agents use this.
And so this will pass the test completion.
But it means that could be something
that that taking time and you're not going to be able to afford.
I'm not going to be able to get to use this new thing
until it gets into different data to get into one of the past, the model
data, and then six months in the future and in the future so that the future.
So this is how you then start to change that and to provide automatic.
And so we're just looking at just looking at identical.
Still going to do the same thing.
But if it's helpful to a different standard.
And then it's that standard operating and structure.
There's a couple of key bits where we saw repeated
instances of this happening so early
with the construction following reverse, so that the tool is doing.
And this is going to be to just kind of
take a
paper ordering to figure out a different categories.
The ones where we saw the biggest improvements
are the ones that are, you know,
where you want to do something a little bit differently,
or whether there isn't as much prior knowledge in the near term data.
So we be in the same conventions and we want to be left is content.
And I hope everyone has a style isn't just run on a hard to write
whatever they want for the walls.
Security, compliance.
Your security policies can be seen.
Organization or infrastructure for editors are not to be something
that's going to be a face off the internet for data processing.
That is a bit more generic,
because there's only so many ways that you can kind of just transform.
Or do you get a whole system step and then testing today?
This one is interesting for me.
It makes a lot of sense
to do something that they've seen costs and all the test differences.
Unique testing is getting structure
to what other countries are doing and that different is better.
So this is kind of these kind of like ones where there is a difference.
And they were able to close the business.
Not sure how much value there is in terms of saying we want to force this
context in.
So investing in structure where the conventions
are local importance for business, that's where the value is.
And then finally, quickly, just in terms of what
you should be measuring and how do you want to be measuring?
I would make the claim that kind of just looking at
that, that's just looking after, that's just looking at the time
when we actually want to be doing is measuring across discovery one is this
one notes from 1 to 100 and 30 or 40.
And just to get down there description.
As it says it takes up 1.2% budget by default.
So you need to figure out a way to actually be assessing whether you're
going for circumstances and to optimize that description.
So they can do that
second trajectory.
So many steps and accessing to do the thing.
Are you looking at the following the intended for flow
that can be used sequence as one and two.
And then the third
one that's going to do the thing that we're going to do to pass the test.
One really interesting
about that is that if you change the around
the model, you can actually move scores by 200%.
And it will have massive differences within the models hold,
because those models are going to be trained extensively on the system models.
So it's not just testing if it's not just in which
the Pacific version of the food or in open hands or in open or in any of the other
and all that, there is a single test, the whole system altogether.
Measurement is how you do this to go from
1 to 2, 12, three, 12, four and
to spend this.
Cool.
So maybe one thing worth mentioning the analysis is open
source is on our website.
Let me share that with you on the on the left side.
So based on everything that you see, like a dimension that we're lacking
in, in our research is a little bit different connection of, you know, output
and outcome is achieved in in relation with the Senate.
I think there's also
amount of uncertainty on appropriate amount of consent.
So we decided to
spend it's and basically published
on the developer status based on our participants.
So what you can do is you can sign up and you can
you can submit your own organization data
and exchange a little bit more data.
So that will help us in the future to connect our research more in terms
of total spend, actually, in terms of the the research organizations that have
integrated with our analysis,
but they're also connecting some of their
agents and labs, and we're also getting extended data from there.
We're not able to budget all of them.
But in terms of modeling, we're working on relooking at like
what's best way to choose tokens
and how to get the most out of them.
Yeah, that's what I had.
Or yeah, here's the the websites
on our lab and the index.
And I think you all know where to go.
And I think we've got a couple of minutes for questions as well.
And so thank you very much Simon.
We've got a question right there.
Thanks.
That was first.
Thank you.
Absolutely brilliant. Thank you so much both of you.
One question about that fascinating switch
in the productivity of engineers
and in your own words, who are now killing it.
I know it may be a bit tricky to collect that dimension of data.
Yeah.
By any chance, did you include age in the groups?
We did not include age,
but we have some level of data.
We have tithing, we have region.
So so there is a bunch of data on
because under some regulation, no data.
Yes, exactly.
People can get out of it.
So we decided to not include that.
But look, we we kind of infer
that more or less by title.
That's some correlation with that.
And some companies that we analyzed all their presenters
and some people are always around for ten plus years.
And we see that.
Thank you.
So I'll just say this and. I tell you.
No no, no I know I know I'm going to say
is it's just it may be interesting for the audience in the room as well.
I go to a lot of events and this is the first one where you have
dev development developer in the title and in the focus,
and the age distribution is very interestingly skewed towards
more senior and experienced, let's call it that way, ages.
That's a very interesting scenario, which I don't see in other events.
I've been curious since the beginning.
Are these the seniors coming back from,
you know, just management into the trenches or is, you know, something else?
But anyway, thank you. If you.
I can tell you one thing with regards to the one
to talk for a minute.
We see a lot of time on staff in here for this year.
So that's why we made a formal data office
that maybe they were helping and it didn't have time to go.
And and now, you know, we have a whole
there are other ways to figure out their time.
They can do really well.
Thank you on this side as well.
I've been reading quite a lot
on line about scenarios where people, sorry, where employees have been given
bad performance ratings explicitly because they are not using AI.
How does that factor into this stat?
And could that bias as a tool, like is it that people who don't want to use
AI are just automatically being treated as not good performers anymore?
No. Because as we look at all Indians, whether or not they use or not.
Yeah.
So, it's we really just look at their output
for the model analysis that should be on first line.
So it's the expert panel algorithmic analysis that most of your output
and have contributed it.
And and based on that we put you in the forecast.
So if you did all of that.
Doesn't matter.
Yeah. We don't look at any data.
So this is really just based on the the radio panel.
Thank you.
We've gone back there
and then one down here.
You mentioned it
matters in what harness the model runs.
Do you regularly publish those data as well?
Maybe I wasn't precise in my language.
It matters that you harness and that you have clear instructions.
Or is it okay? Sorry. Yeah.
We made the claim that it does matter.
You're probably a better bet.
So that's just about.
Where we've done this 1950s to have a look at the communications
of all the learning system and what what we want to do that
moving forward to be sharing those numbers more widely.
So it's a bit of answer, but also on the after
everything else is going to be those.
And maybe maybe share them like right on a regular basis. Yep.
Not just one paper. Yeah. Great.
We're going to draw, you know, all the rules as well.
Just when you know there's a lot of people don't understand how performance.
Great.
Thank you. And I think we had another question today.
Oh another couple of questions down here.
We're okay for a couple more.
Thanks again.
Just questions for Rob.
I think you mentioned in one of your slides that
there is a code structure quality that you unlock,
or you've come to consensus or there's some, some idea
that the quality of the code matters or has an influence in the outcome to you.
Do you have like an idea of what that quality is, what conventions it is?
I mean, it doesn't have to be a concrete answer, but like following
some of the engineering practices related qualities, or you've come up
with some new ways of doing this that will help improve the outcomes.
So I think what we are looking at more specifically is just kind of
following any instructions specifically, not degeneration, but there's
going by
clicking code or any other kind of any tangles, because
that is very particular to normalization in terms of how they want to reconcile
and to have a kind of like a manufacturing technology decision.
So no, we didn't know about that.
It's been really.
Was there any kind of findings from what you get to them,
like how people structure kind of principles of like
to go with that, that kind of get back to the performance.
We don't look at this specifically.
We're actually working on a paper that we're getting ready with application
performance management tools
that will give us staff dimensions, that we have nothing back.
So so there is some, some, some thought or inquisitive
on code quality might have an impact.
And you have investigated yet.
So we when I go back to the initial let me show you on the radio panel.
So there are questions on on quality and
quality.
That's pretty subjective.
So and if you can look at that maybe you see there is
this is a good question with the lowest removed
we have since then done separate
panel analysis specifically on maintenance and in terms
of how easy it is to maintain it if there is significant and higher.
So that's all we use is now.
Now this is when we talk about making ability,
whether that up or down that's going to use.
Adjusted name.
I'm interested.
In the in the diagram we're looking at before where people do.
I mean how long is it taking people to get into these high performing states.
And you know, what
can you see what kind of triggers there are and what kind of things are?
You know, the high performer is kind of getting there very quickly.
Or are people gradually still moving across into these things?
Because your first graph of the kind of exponential growth
showed a very fast take off
very recently, but I kind of interested in like how are people getting there?
Do you understand what triggers and is it is it is it something that they can
people are still. Hitting for. Interesting.
We just haven't done.
Yeah.
We we take note that this is how it is.
What we see is that.
So once you're classified
as AI top performer you tend to say that.
So it seems to be a mindset which that takes place.
And we see that like when you have a that are very strongly
I feel like they just.
I guess even if you're having an individual,
you know, sprint into it, you know how to do it.
If you don't have to drag your team along, then you will be able to keep it.
Yeah.
I mean, the
same thing is a very interesting measure because I know people who have left
because the rest of their team is not working in a way that's compatible
with them and things like that.
And so the team trying to understand the team dynamic changes
would be interesting as well.
Sure, our some of our study participants access to an analysis
that is entitled to feel that they're losing. Our
farmers are hiring farmers.
So they do all that we we have and we offer them a panel.
And they couldn't in principle look at it.
It's just such an interesting.
Okay. I'm afraid.
That's all we've got time for now.
So thank you again to Rob and Simon.
We're now going into a break,